Finding Aid for Weston E. Vivian Papers 1964-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Weston E. Vivian Papers 1964-1968
Vivian, Weston Edward, 1924-
Democratic US Congressman from the 2nd Michigan Congressional District, 1965-1967. Campaign files, 1964, 1966 and 1968; files documenting his activities as member of the 89th Congress; subject files detailing views of constituents on such subjects as the Vietnam War, civil rights, Lyndon Johnson's anti-poverty program, and other issues of the 1960s; also clippings, photographs, and audio tapes.
86184 Aa 2; UAm
12 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Congressman Weston Vivian (donor no. 4364 ) and came to the library beginning in 1967.
The collection is open for research.
Weston E. Vivian served as United States Congressman, 1965-1966, for the Second Congressional District of southeastern Michigan. A liberal Democrat aided by the 1964 landslide election of Lyndon Johnson, Vivian won a narrow victory in the traditionally Republican 2nd district that included Lenawee, Livingston, Monroe, Washtenaw, and part of Wayne county. Vivian was defeated in his bid for reelection in 1966 and failed in an attempt to regain the office in 1968.
Vivian was born October 25, 1924 in Newfoundland, Canada. The family moved to the United States in 1929. Vivian served in the US Navy, 1943-1946, during which time he received a BS degree in engineering from Union College, Schenectady, NY, through the Navy's V-12 program. He later earned a master's degree in electrical engineering from MIT, 1949, and a Ph.D. in engineering from the University of Michigan, 1959.
Vivian worked for the Boeing Company and Sperry Gyroscope Company, 1946-1951, after which he was employed by the University of Michigan, 1951-1960, as a research engineer and lecturer. In 1960 Vivian was one of the founders of Conductron Corporation, an electrical and aeronautical engineering research and manufacturing company headquartered in Ann Arbor. Vivian served as a vice-president and member of the board of directors of Conductron from 1960 to 1964. After his election to Congress, Vivian resigned his positions with the company.
Vivian was an unsuccessful candidate for the Ann Arbor city council in 1959. He served as chairman of the Ann Arbor City Democratic Party, 1960-1962. In 1964 Vivian won the Democratic nomination for the House of Representatives in a three-way primary contest. In the general election he defeated incumbent Republican George Meader with 50.8% of the vote. Vivian, the first Ph.D. professional engineer to serve in Congress, was appointed to the Space and Astronautics Committee where his technical expertise gave him unusual influence for a freshman congressman.
Other areas of particular interest to Congressman Vivian were civil rights, civil liberties, the War on Poverty program, normalization of relations with China, and US policy in Vietnam. Vivian was a strong supporter of the 1965 Voting Rights Act and the 1966 civil rights bill. He was one of the sponsors of the House resolution challenging the seating of the Mississippi congressional delegation in favor of the candidates of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party. He also served as one of the congressional observers during the civil rights demonstrations in Selma, Alabama. Originally a supporter of President Johnson's policy in Vietnam, Vivian gradually developed increasing reservations about the US role in the war, eventually favoring a gradual US military withdrawal from Vietnam. Vivian broke with the Johnson administration on the issue in 1968 and organized the Robert Kennedy for President Committee of Washtenaw County.
Vivian was among the vulnerable Democratic congressmen targeted for defeat by the Republican Party in 1966. He was narrowly defeated by Marvin Esch in the general election that also included a write-in campaign for "peace-candidate" Elise Boulding. Vivian attempted to regain the 2nd district congressional seat in 1968. He defeated Jerry Dupont in the Democratic primary but again lost to Esch in the general election.
The Weston E. Vivian papers document his three campaigns for the US House of Representatives in 1964, 1966, and 1968, and his service in the 89th Congress, 1965-1966. The papers include correspondence, speeches, campaign literature, texts of radio broadcasts and campaign advertisements, press releases and newsletters, newspaper clippings, photographs, and sound and video recordings. Also included in the Vivian papers are three University of Michigan student papers on the 1966 and 1968 Vivian congressional campaigns.
The collection is divided into several distinct series: biographical material, congressional campaigns, congressional service, subject files, clippings, photographs, and sound recordings and motion picture tapes. The additional material received in 1990 is located in boxes 11-12, but has been integrated into the appropriate place in the contents listing.
Subjects:
Civil rights--United States.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Poverty.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1964.; United States--Congress--Elections--1966.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1968.; United States. Congress. House.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Material:
Children.; Head Start programs.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; Monroe (Mich.); Peterson, Esther, 1906-1997; Political elections--1964.; Political elections--1966.; Politics and government--1961-1970.; Space flight.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration.; Vivian, Weston Edward, 1924-; Vivian family.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Vivian, Weston Edward, 1924-; Elections--Michigan--1964.; Elections--Michigan--1966.; Elections--Michigan--1968.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Material filed at the beginning of the collection contains several biographical sketches and magazine articles about Vivian.
  - Biographical sketches and related (Box 1)
- Congressional Campaigns
  The series for each of the Congressional Campaigns includes speeches and press statements by Vivian, campaign brochures and literature, correspondence and background material dealing with election issues and campaign strategy, texts of radio advertisements, and information on the voting records of Vivian's opponents. The 1966 campaign series includes material from the Elise Boulding campaign and the 1968 series contains newsletters and other material from the Michigan Conference of Concerned Democrats and the New Democratic Coalition of Michigan.
  - 1964
    - Speeches and Press Statements, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Brochures and Campaign Literature (Box 1)
    - Radio Advertising (Box 1)
    - Background Material (Box 1)
    - Primary Election (Box 1)
    - George Meader Voting Record (Box 1)
  - 1966
    - Brochures and Campaign Literature (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Advertisements (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and Background Material, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - District Political Organization (Box 1)
    - Boulding Campaign (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Student Papers on 1966 Vivian Campaign
      - "The 1966 Campaign of United States Congressman Weston E. Vivian" by Jared H. Becker (Box 1)
      - "A Study of the Political Campaign of Weston E. Vivian," by Evy Eugene (Box 1)
    - Binder containing positions on various issues (Box 12)
  - 1968
    - Speeches, Position Papers, Press Releases (Box 1)
    - Brochures and Campaign Literature (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and Background Material (Box 1)
    - Radio Advertising (Box 1)
    - Jerome Dupont Primary Campaign (Box 1)
    - Marvin Esch Voting Record (Box 1)
    - Election Statistics (Box 1)
    - Michigan Conference of Concerned Democrats (Box 1)
    - New Democratic Coalition of Michigan (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Student Paper on 1968 Vivian Campaign (Box 1)
    - "The Wes Vivian Story, Chapter 1968," by Benjamin C. Stanczyk (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Ann Arbor-Washtenaw County Democratic Party newsletters 1964-1968 (Box 12)
    - "The Bedford Democrat" 1965-1966 (Box 12)
    - Arlene Handy letters (constituent mail) (Box 12)
- Congressional Service
  The Congressional Service section relates to Vivian's activities as a member of the 89th Congress. Included here are a bills file of legislation introduced by Vivian, press releases, Vivian's district newsletter and weekly newspaper columns, a constituent questionnaire, and copies of Vivian's floor speeches and other "remarks" as printed in the Congressional Record. There is also a subject index to the Congressional Record excerpts.
  - Bills File, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Press Releases January 1965-December 1966, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Newsletter (Box 2)
  - Responses to Newsletter (Box 2)
  - Weekly Newspaper Column (Box 2)
  - Constituent Questionnaire (Box 2)
  - Radio Broadcasts (Box 2)
  - Speeches (Box 2)
  - Congressional Record-"Remarks" (Box 2)
  - Index to Congressional Record (Box 2)
  - Entries made by WEV in the Congressional Record, 89th Congress (Box 12)
  - Roll call votes, 89th Congress (Box 12)
  - Video Recording (Box 2)
  - Speeches (1990 accession)
    - October 1964-September 1966 (Box 11)
    - October 1966-June 1969 (Box 12)
- Subject Files
  The Subject Files consist principally of constituent correspondence but also include some analytical reports and other material on particular issues. Among the significant subjects in this series are the Vietnam War, civil rights, civil liberties and the House Un-American Activities Committee, natural resources and pollution, the Atomic Energy Commission's selection of a site for a nuclear accelerator, and the War on Poverty.
  - Aid to Private Schools, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Arts and Humanities Foundation (Box 3)
  - Auto Safety (Box 3)
  - China (Box 12)
  - Civil Defense (Box 3)
  - Civil Rights
    Correspondence in the Civil Rights subject file includes letters on the civil rights movement in general, the 1965 Voting Rights Act, and the 1966 civil rights bill. The Mississippi-Freedom Democratic Party file includes correspondence from several University of Michigan students working as volunteers for the Student Non-violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) in Mississippi. There are also letters from participants in the Selma, Alabama civil rights demonstration. The civil rights file contains some information on local civil rights activities, most notably a draft statement by Vivian on the Ann Arbor open housing ordinance.
    - General (Box 3)
    - Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP) (Box 3)
    - Selma, Alabama Demonstrations (Box 3)
    - 1965 Voting Rights Bill (Box 3)
    - 1966 Civil Rights Bill, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor Open Housing Ordinance (Box 3)
  - Congressional Reorganization (Box 4)
  - Copyright Legislation (Box 4)
  - Currency Bill (Box 4)
  - Economy (Box 4)
  - Education, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Elementary and secondary education (Box 12)
  - Farm Bill (Box 4)
  - Foreign Policy
    - General, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Foreign Aid (Box 4)
    - China, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Vietnam, 7 folders (Box 4)
      The Vietnam War subject file contains letters expressing the full range of opinions on US policy in Vietnam and also reflects Vivian's evolving position on the war. The correspondence includes information on the emergence of the anti-war movement in Ann Arbor, the organization of the first anti-war teach-ins at the University of Michigan, and, to a lesser extent, on radical organizations such as the Voice Party and Students for a Democratic Society. Among the correspondents are many early opponents of the war, including Carl Oglesby and Anatol Rapaport.
    - Vietnam, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Foreign Trade (Box 5)
  - Gun Control, "Dodd Bill", 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Housing/Demonstration Cities Act (Box 5)
  - House Un-American Activities Committee, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Immigration Bill (Box 5)
  - Labor
    - General (Box 5)
    - Fair Employment Practices Bill (Box 5)
    - Migrant Workers, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Situs Picketing Bill (Box 6)
    - Taft-Hartley Act, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Unemployment Compensation Bill (Box 6)
  - Laboratory Animal Protection (Box 6)
  - Legislative Reapportionment, "Dirksen Amendment" (Box 6)
  - Medicare Bill, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - National Resources/Pollution
    The natural resources/pollution file contains correspondence and technical reports on proposed development of the Huron River watershed including the Mill Creek Reservoir, and the Raisin River watershed.
    - General, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - National Park and Monuments (Box 7)
    - Huron River Watershed Development, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Mill Creek Reservoir, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Raisin River Watershed (Box 7)
  - Nuclear Accelerator Site Selection, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Regulation of Industry (Box 7)
  - Taxation (Box 7)
  - Tornado Damage 1965 (Box 7)
  - Unidentified Flying Objects (Box 7)
  - United States Capital Building Remodeling (Box 7)
  - United Nations (Box 8)
  - War on Poverty Program
    The War on Poverty file consists of constituent letters on the overall anti-poverty program of the Johnson Administration and on several local anti-poverty projects, in particular, the Willow Run Association for Neighborhood Development (WRAND). Originally sponsored by the Institute for Labor and Industrial Relations of the University of Michigan and Wayne State University, WRAND was one of the first demonstration projects approved by the federal Office of Economic Opportunity. WRAND-was the subject of considerable publicity and controversy, both locally and nationally.
    - General, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Adrian Opportunity Exchange (Box 8)
    - Washtenaw County Citizens for Economic Opportunity (Box 8)
    - WRAND (Willow Run Association for Neighborhood Development), 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Ypsilanti Greek Theatre (Box 8)
- Newspaper Clippings
  The Newspaper Clippings series covers Vivian's term in Congress.
  - January 1965-April 30, 1966 (Box 8)
  - May 1-December 24, 1966, 12 folders (Box 9)
  - 1959 Ann Arbor City Council Campaign (Box 9)
- Photographs
  The Photographs consist of portraits of Vivian and his family and of colleagues active in state and national politics; campaign photos; photos of Vivian with Hubert Humphrey, Robert Kennedy, Edward Kennedy, Esther Peterson, and other public figures; photos of Vivian as member of congressional delegation visiting NASA site; and miscellaneous photos relating to Vivian's personal and professional life.
  - Awards (Box 9)
  - Brooks Air Force Base, 12th Annual Science and Engineering Symposium October 12-14, 1965 (Box 9)
  - Campaign of 1964 (Box 9)
  - Campaign of 1965 (Box 9)
  - Colleagues and friends (includes portraits of several presidents) (Box 9)
  - Esch, Marvin L. (Box 9)
  - Family (Box 9)
  - Groups
    - Capitol background (Box 9)
    - Congressional and other formal (also UAm) (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Headstart (Box 9)
  - Hubert H. Humphrey (Box 9)
  - Hubert H. Humphrey in Monroe, Michigan (Box 9)
  - Kennedy, Robert F. and Edward M. (also oversize folder UAm) (Box 9)
  - Michigan constituents and students (Box 9)
  - NASA, official photographs (Box 9)
  - NASA, other photographs (Box 9)
  - Peterson, Esther (Box 9)
  - Portraits, formal (Box 9)
  - Portraits, informal (Box 9)
  - Udall, Stewart (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
- Sound recordings and motion picture tapes
  The sound recordings consist of reel-to-reel tapes of different speeches and radio broadcasts by Vivian, remarks from a business development conference sponsored by Vivian, campaign radio advertisements, and speeches by Vice-President Hubert Humphrey and Senator Edward Kennedy. The tapes are not individually described.
  - Audio-tapes 3", 27 tapes (Box 10)
  - Audio-tapes 5", 45 tapes (Box 10)
  - Audio-tapes 7", 14 tapes (Box 10)
  - Motion picture tapes (Box 10)